Welcome back to the AMR uh roundt on
overtures discussion for the 2026 PCA
general assembly. This is uh our third
video and in this segment we're going to
be talking about overtures dealing with
uh judicial matters and administrative
and polity matters. If you missed the
first two parts uh go find those at the
AMR YouTube channel or on the Substack.
But we're going to dive right in. Uh
I've got uh Dr. David Coffin and Dr.
Steve Typton and Howie Dano here uh and
they've been great sharing their
thoughts so far. So, we're going to dive
into uh what they think about some of
the judicial overtures that were sent up
this year. We're going to start um with
overture 27 from Westminster. And this
is uh coming back to an issue that's had
some discussion for a number of years,
but we've never really had any
resolution on. And that's the issue of
uh assumption of original jurisdiction.
So, Howie, I'm going to let you speak to
that first.
Yeah, I've tried to get over passed uh
at least twice in the last 20 years to
fix this thing as it is right now
because it says um if a lower court
refuses to act
and that's a phrase is a little too
vague. I think it should should say
something more specific and measurable
like declines to indict. Um but if we do
that then we need to bump the threshold
up much higher than two presbyteries. Um
I suggest 20% of the presbyteries
instead of two. Uh we had a case a few
years ago out of a Midwest presbyter
caused a lot of turmoil. If this chapter
had been fixed, it would not have caused
as much turmoil. So um I'll probably try
to move to amend this. I don't like it
in its current form by any means, but I
do like the idea of trying to fix 341 to
make it uh reasonable. Um, and it um
it's going to be hard to find out where
that perfect spot is in order to get 58
predatories to approve it. But I think
um I think there's got to be a spot of
some sort and it's probably how high or
low should the threshold be probably.
>> Yeah, Steve, I think you were on the
same page on that. something about an
amendment. What do you think?
>> Yeah. So, um
I'm not certain what that number is,
right? Uh percentage- wise, like I mean,
so let's say that 70% of the PCA would
be happy with 15%
and how he's the lone person who votes
against it because he thinks it's too
low. Like that's that's the issue. And
he's shaking his head. But my point is
is like trying to figure out what that
delta is uh is going to be important. Um
and perhaps
I'm I'm also concerned about the
procedure
because it makes it sound like as it's
written that it, you know, that it goes
to the general assembly
and but it also doesn't say how. Does
the assembly get to vote in the summer
on whether or not to assume original
jurisdiction? What does that discussion
look like? Um how does that go? You
know, so um in that sense, I if it is
envisioned as a discussion in a vote at
the general assembly, then maybe a lower
number is is fair. But if it's saying it
just automatically goes to the SJC and
they automatically
uh take it up. Um that's a that's a
different issue. But contrary to how
he's shaking his head, I mean it just
says it may assume as written right now.
So I mean it it's somewhat confusing to
me what the procedure is. Um, I'm not
all that interested in a discussion on
the floor of the assembly about the
potential sins of a man and then we all
get to vote on whether or not as a the
largest grand jury ever or whatever. So,
I I think it's an important part of our
polity. Um,
but I agree it's unworkable as written.
and it's just trying to figure out where
the consensus can be on creating
something that that could work. Uh I
also think it's helpful that it's
somewhat downstream from the issues that
Howie was talking about that this isn't
about an individual. This isn't let's
change the BCO so that we can finally
get Howie Dano who we've all you know
desire well but that's not what this is
about. So, let's try to figure out what
is what is a proper way of doing it. So,
that's all.
>> So, it' be less reactive because it's
not there's not a particular case
everyone's chomping at the bit for,
right? Yeah.
>> David, you you have thoughts on this? I
know you've you've been thinking about
original jurisdiction, I remember, from
several years ago. What do you think
about this?
>> I I think both uh 341 and 331 are a
serious mistake.
Um 341
was is a novelty in terms of
Presbyterian polity. It was invented
when the PCA came into existence. We
live for 20 let's see 80 well any case
we live for a long time and 331 didn't
have that provision in sessions and
elders.
uh it came in in the that ad interim
committee on restructure that I was
unhappy to have served on. Um and I
think both of them are a serious
mistake.
Uh I think that uh
all of them almost demand a denial of
due process.
What's the evidentary standard for
people hearing what's going on in a
presbyter?
And um how is that evidence then
presented to the court above that would
have original jurisdiction?
Um the uh we have other means to um the
the the fact it came out of one case in
the old southern church. Um
not going to be able to bring his name
up. The great historian of the southern
church at Union Seminary. Um
uh in any case uh he had gone off the
rails people thought in his doctrine and
his presbyterary protected him but they
wouldn't and they couldn't get at it and
so that was all on their minds and they
wanted some means like that. That's
where 341 came from. Um
the
with be with the 40-5
we have a way to get at a matter if it
we need to uh with reports that have to
be credible and so on. We don't need
this business of presbyteries ganging
up. I mean who one presence
and they start to spread it around.
Well, then for the other ne next price
trade down, it's secondhand. It's it's
hearsay.
Um
I I think this is a really bad idea to
even have it as it is. And I think this
version of it that's being proposed
makes it even worse.
It does seem like 40-5 has been like
this new discovery in the PCA where
everyone realized there's this mechanism
and that's that kind of took the heat
off of uh you know original jurisdiction
questions for a while but we did still
have this one. Okay. What about um
Overure 16 from Southwest Florida
clarifying circularization of the court
regarding complaints.
>> I love it.
>> Oh, you love it. Okay, go for it. Yeah,
I mean it actually came up at an SJC
case that we had and um the book
presently says if there's a complaint
filed at presbyter for example,
nobody can circulate any pros and cons
um prior to the consideration of that at
the presbyter meeting which seems to be
counterproductive to uh discussion. Um
what the author of the overture
I think rightly identified was it's the
appellet court that you can't
circularize not the original court. Uh
if my president is considering a matter
because a complaint to the original
court is essentially just a motion to
amend something previously adopted.
Well, so if I file it and I call it
motion to amend something previously
adopted, everybody can circulate
whatever they want. If I call it a
complaint, they can't, even though the
consideration of it is going to be the
same. So, I think it's a a very helpful
um fix of the BCO.
>> I think you Yeah, you other gentlemen
seem to agree with that. Is that
correct?
>> Yeah. Yes.
>> All right. Well, then let's move on to
overture 28. Uh, this is about members
complaints in a session referenced
matter and it looked like two of you
supported it, but uh, David, looks like
you were thinking no on this one. So,
uh, why don't you guys first speak to
it? Steve, do you want to speak to it
and why you think it might be a good
idea?
>> I could try. Um, so I I will say David's
comments have have certainly given me uh
much pause for thought, but um
so obviously reference takes a matter
from a court of original jurisdiction
and transfers it to a hire. Uh and while
that in and of itself is is not is not
an insignificant matter, right? Because
one of the things you're doing is you're
losing a level of appeal when you do
that. So, uh, it's not as bad when a
session goes to Presbyter. It's
dramatically different when Presbyter
sends something to the SJC as happened
with Central Indiana. There's no appeal.
It it just is what it is or or even
complaint for that matter, even if it
was found not guilty or whatever. So, I
I I understand that the the differences.
One of the things that I'm more
concerned about, and this maybe has more
to do with a session than it does with a
presbyter, is oftentimes when you have a
session level, let's say a trial for
instance, um, and you have all of these
ruling elders who've been dealing with
the issue pastorally,
uh, in formal discipline for a number of
for a while, and then it gets to the
point where you need to to actually take
the steps of formal discipline. And all
of them are so intricately involved in
everything that's been going on that
they feel maybe they're the ones that
say, "Look, we're not sure we can do a
trial properly or maybe there's only two
of us and one of us has to be the
prosecutor and the other has to be well,
how are we going to how are we going to
handle this?" And so they send it up to
the presbyter. Well, now that individual
has no right to complain. I mean,
obviously that's an appeal that's
slightly different, but those issues it
could be easy to just
and that issue I I can see where it's
it's understandable why it's being
referenced. But if if somebody looks at
this and gets wise to the fact that well
if I just reference it to presbyary this
guy can't no longer has standing then it
could be it could be used in a in a in a
nefarious so to speak way to send it to
presbyary because no matter what happens
nobody can none of my people can
complain about it. I'm not suggesting
anybody has ever has nefarious motives
in the PCA. Uh but I I think it it
showed a potential loophole that could
be closed and whether it just needs to
be clarified, amended, or whatever. I
think the sentiment is good. Whether or
not it's well written may be a different
question. But I think to try to preserve
that that right of complaint um when
those actions are referenced, I I think
could be could be helpful.
I've reviewed enough cases in 28 years
on the SJC. I don't want to give anybody
a loophole.
>> Well, you you wonder how somebody even
thought of this unless there was a
situation where, you know,
>> Yeah. And reference matters are very
rare.
In my 40 40 years as an elder, I've only
voted in favor of accepting a reference
once and it was a central Indiana case
because that presbyter it was
challenging for them and they asked us
to take it up. Um
I don't know why you would take the
presbyter why you would accept a
complaint reference from the session
just say no you guys deal with it. They
said well we're we're divided. I said,
"I don't care. Take a vote. How many
guy, you know, and if if the complainant
isn't satisfied, they bring it to us.
Why would we take your complaint?" I
can't imagine accepting a complaint from
a session as a reference.
>> Well, I don't think that's the issue,
though. I mean it it it would fall into
the category of it but but it's it's
really in one sense anytime a session
references something to the presbyter
uh you know any kind of difficult
decision whether it's a judicial case uh
or it is some other issue that they're
they're struggling with. So it's not it
wouldn't exclude the option to to
reference a complaint but I think that's
only one of the options not not even the
primary one necessarily.
David, do you have any thoughts on this
one?
>> Um, I'm opposed to it. Um,
I think in the nature of the case, a
reference changes all of the rights and
responsibilities that people have and
some are lost and it's a trade-off.
They're lost because they hope to have
the higher court be able to handle
something they couldn't handle. Uh, but
why you should try and
reconstitute one group's rights and
responsibilities when there are many
more. What happens with a a complaint?
But the further a complaint is defined
as
uh uh
opposition to an act of a court by one
under that jurisdiction. These people
are not under that jurisdiction.
it violates the very nature of a
complaint as we have it in 40 431.
So I I think and and I also think and
maybe that's what I'm not sure whether
this is what how was getting at but the
the it may well be Steve if I agree with
you that someone might say oh well
here's good technique to get out of
responsibility we we'll send up
complaints to the presbyter but I don't
think our presbyter has ever received a
complaint
and if there was any hint that it was
actually being done as a technique to
avoid responsibility. I'm sure the
prespitary wouldn't do it. So, I I I
hope that this does not pass.
Okay, let's jump over to overture 69,
um, which is about clarifying the
contents of the record in a judicial
case. I wanted to give David a chance to
speak to this one.
Um
this is really a very fine piece of
work. Um the SJC has struggled time and
time again with the fact that there are
instructions in various places in the
rules of discipline that talk about the
record that are not entirely consistent
right now.
you can interpretively make them
consistent, but and the SJC has had to
do that uh in decisions,
but folk who are trying to figure out
the clerks of sessions are trying to
figure out what their responsibilities
are
uh could easily be confused and it mean
we we've had to do some serious things
uh dealing with records of the case and
um it's I'm sure this is Jim who
prepared this. Do you think Howie? Yeah,
>> I'm sure it is.
>> He's a lawyer on the SJC and he has had
to face uh and on panels a number of
these cases. I think he's done an
outstanding job in and bring the whole
thing into consistency. If I'm
misreading that Steve or Howie, I'm glad
to hear it. But I I think he's done very
good job.
>> Yeah, I think it's great.
Okay, sounds like everyone's in favor of
that. Um, let's talk about overure 35
briefly. This is about establishing a
deadline for issuing indictments. So, we
talked about there's a particular case
where there was a long delay recently
and that that's the occasion for this
one. What do you all think about this?
Well, I don't think it can stand as
written because um if the prosecutor
doesn't bring an indictment in 60 days,
it says you have to appoint a new
prosecutor.
Well, now that guy's got to get up to
speed. So, it doesn't really expedite
anything. Um,
it's I think this the first time in my
time on the SJC where I've seen this be
an issue in a case.
So maybe it's, you know, trying to fix
that oneoff thing that um but um if we
were going to fix it, I'd rather see if
the indictment isn't brought within X
number of days, the court has to drop
the charges.
So whether that's 90 days or 120 days,
but the idea of just, you know, what if
that second prosecutor doesn't bring the
indictment? Let's say it's complicated.
it's hard to get hold of the key
witnesses and now it's another 60-day
passes and they appoint the third
prosecutor. So, I don't think the
solution proposed by although I've
spoken to the author, I think he's
planning to bring it an amendment of
some sort to the overures committee.
He's on the overtures committee, so
we'll see.
Steve, do you have a thought?
>> Yeah, I mean, again, I I echo what what
Howie said. Um, again, I'm not
necessarily
keen on all of the different pieces and
parts, but I I think uh having some sort
of uh deadline uh is important. And I
think it would be wise to push it out
far enough that uh
the only thing it's going to catch is,
you know, situations where a presbyter
is just not doing its job versus this is
complex. it's going to take more than 60
days or whatever. Uh but you know, in
theory, you could have, you know, a
pre-trial suspension
not by way of censure indefinitely while
a prosecutor and a presbyterary is
willing to to allow it to go on or you
end up having to complain about it and
then having to deal with that whole
complaint process. So,
David, do you have a thought? No, I I
I'm against it. Um I know I I hadn't
realized there was one instance. I've
never seen an instance beyond that, but
I don't think we ought to change the
book because we have one uh
renegade prosecutor.
>> Then 067 from Battoic um is about
preliminary requirements before citing
the court to appear regarding a 40-5
report. So, my understanding is this
came up because we, like I said, we've
had a lot more 404 40-5s come up
recently. A lot of those have been going
to RPR. There's been confusion about
exactly what the process is and what the
standard is. And it sounds like this is
at least aimed at trying to clarify some
of that. What do you guys think about
this approach?
How and Steve, it looks like y'all are
in favor and and David, you were
thinking no. Well, I mean this this is
the process that RPR has used for a
number of years, right? Um we we we make
a recommendation to the assembly to find
that it is a credible report and that it
uh reports an important delinquency or
grossly unconstitutional act. Um I I
think that the language of 40-5 is is
relatively clear in the sense that
that's what needs to happen. Um I I I'm
actually not in favor of it. Uh okay.
Maybe
>> Yeah. I I don't think it's necessary. So
I I think that it's clear enough in the
statute that that's if if if that's the
kind of report you're supposed to be
acting on, then it seems incumbent to me
that you would make those two
determinations.
um on some level whether it's formal or
informal
you have to decide it's credible and it
it it it meets a particular standard. Um
I I wouldn't I'm not saying that I would
necessarily fight hard against it. I
just don't think it's it's necessary and
I don't it's not high on my list of
really important overures. So
Oh, why don't you go next and then David
you can you can respond finally.
Part of me thinks it's important because
of
the number of 40-5 letters that were
flying around this year. I agree with
Stephen that it seems like a no-brainer
that you would try to decide well is
what being alleged an important
delinquency or you know you take a vote
or you have a commission or a committee
that's empowered to do this to say
listen um
somebody's alleging my
uh session doesn't use himnils
I it fails on question one right there
right so we don't do anything else. Um,
is there sufficient evidence provided to
support the allegation?
Um, well, you'd you'd want that. You'd
probably call whoever's
sending the letter and say, "How do you
know that session didn't consider that?"
Or, "How do you know?" So, um, I don't
mind codifying it. I think it probably
be helpful to cottify it. Um, it's still
it doesn't give presbyaries less
freedom. It just makes it clear to
uh any court that thinks you shouldn't
do those two things before citing. I
mean, if a presbyperary doesn't do those
two things and they cite a session to
respond,
uh, they're probably going to regret
that they didn't do those two things
first. So, I think it's a good idea.
>> Okay, David, what do you think about
this?
Um I think the language is there is uh
perfectly appropriate. But um if we
change it then a um established history
of judicial construction is gone
and we've got a whole new set of words
and and and uh to interpret and who
knows how they're going to be
interpreted when there is a conflict and
people are all looking for ways to get
around this that or the other which
always happens in judicial
interpretation.
Um there's we have it's not only the
current language but it's the history of
the interpretation of that language is
so full and finished I I don't see any
reason to abandon that tradition and
have to start all over again.
>> Does the history support this language
as the proper steps to take? Oh, okay.
>> Well, it it supports the current
language that's in the book. We don't
know whether it supports this new
language because that's going to have to
be construed.
That's the whole point
>> you're talking about.
>> My question my question is has it
>> has it been construed this way
historically?
>> It has been construed
consistent with the language that's in
the book now. We don't have any
construction of the
>> I want this new I want this new language
that
Okay.
>> Well, Derek, I was going to say I I
might be in favor of amending it if we
add a sentence at the bottom that says
this is not a quick route to take to
deal with the matter. Please be advised
you might wait up to a year before
anything happens on your your report or
something along those lines because
people think 40-5 I I I'll get an answer
next week from the assembly that they've
kicked such and such presbyter out of
the denomination because of what I
reported. So,
okay, David, you're talking about the
language of credible report. You're
saying that has a history in our
denomination, how that's been
understood. Is that what you're
referring to?
>> Precisely. Well, not just credible
report. Credible report
has to be either um the the a serious
defect or a gross
>> Yeah. important delinquency or grossly
unconstitutional proceeding.
>> Right. So important delinquency that's
construed to be uh a um uh sin of
omission but one that is sign very
significant and gross uh delinquence or
gross
>> unconstitutional proceeding
>> proceeding is a sin of commission and
that has to be a major sin not any kind
of minor things that's the construction
of it And um but with this new language,
we're going to start a new interpretive
tradition. And I don't think there's any
reason to roll the dice to hope that
it's going to be as solid as it is right
now.
Okay. I I could be wrong, but it's my
understanding is is that language is
still in the proposal, but I could be
wrong about that. Um,
>> well, it it it is, but it's in a
different uh place.
>> Remind me of the number we're talking
about.
>> We're on 67. I mean, it retains the
original phrasing in the first paragraph
and then repeats it in one and two. What
it's trying to avoid, I think, is a
court that when they get a 40-5 letter,
the first thing they do is cite the
lower court to appear. And that seems
precipitous. The overture seems to be
saying you've got to uh decide what kind
of a category of an allegation it is and
is there sufficient evidence to support
it and then you can cite them to appear.
Um
there are
um when a report comes to the uh
higher court under the current language,
it has to be understood to be credible.
That's the first thing,
>> right?
>> You've taken that away. Now you're just
any report. No, just wait a minute. Now
you're receiving any report
but you have to follow these
determinations.
Um the uh but it doesn't really
have you under one and two paying
attention to grossly unconstitutional
proceedings and important delinquency.
It introduces
uh uh
well in fact it it reverses the order.
It it has grossly unconstitutional be
first and and uh sufficient evidence
isn't exactly the same thing as
credible.
That's a different meaning. Yeah, that's
where the I think that is where the big
change is is they've stricken credible
report and then they've specified the
the type of support or a report it needs
to be to be um advanced. So, okay.
>> Well, I think it's a I think it's
amendable. It does say it does use
credible only in front of the word
source which is different than credible
report but I think you could leave you
could unstrike credible in the first
line and leave that in and flip one and
two. Um but so I I mean I think it's
amendable but um I think it tries to
address the situation where
this happened in uh Pittsburgh Presbyter
where uh session got cited to appear and
answer
and they got there and preser realized
well it wasn't a important delinquency
or gross proceeding or it wasn't a
credible
report and now a session had been cited
to appear and answer and it seemed like
it was jumping the gun I guess.
>> All right. The only thing I want to add
is what was is that there is something
added to it right and I think somebody
mentioned it before but just to
underline it that it's adding sufficient
evidence provided to support the
allegation. Um, you know, whether or not
that that is included in the concept of
a credible report is a debatable
question, but it certainly is adding a a
standard that is not currently there.
So,
>> well, let me just say I'm sure there's
nothing but good intentions behind this
because it came from PTOIC Presbyter.
>> All right. Yes.
>> Okay. Well, let's uh I think we're going
to skip over Richard 46. I think all of
you said no to that. that's about public
allegations online and and kind of going
to uh charges and everyone said that's
not a good idea. So, I'm going to say,
is there anything else under judicial
overtures y'all want to talk about?
Otherwise, we're going to skip. There's
quite a few other ones that we're not
even going to speak to that y'all didn't
seem to think were worth commenting on.
Okay. All right. Well, then we'll
address here in our last part uh
overures that deal with administrative
issues and policy issues. Um so one that
stood out that it seemed like a number
of folks thought was worth talking about
was overure 59 uh a non-judicial removal
of a member from the role at their
request. Um I think Howie you said this
is an important one. Do you want to
speak to that?
Uh I don't think it can pass 58 uh
presbyteries.
Uh this kind of gets way back to the
Chen case back in the dinosaur days.
David will remember that case. Um
uh the paragraph presently says
um the scenario in the present wording
is that when he's affiliated
with that other entity and this change
is when he's affiliated or says he plans
to affiliate and
um
I have lukewarm sympathy but some
sympathy for
Okay. The other you other guys did not
want to see this one pass if I
understand you correctly.
>> Steve, you want to speak to that?
>> Um well, maybe David because I think it
was his comment that sort of flipped me.
Okay. Anyway,
>> David, maybe David could start.
>> Well, um the um a church member doesn't
have the right to have his church
membership dissolved immediately. That's
just simple. So the whole premise of the
problem they want to solve is is a valid
premise.
Um
the uh
and furthermore
if the church doesn't delay until he has
actually attempted to or
accomplished moving into another
denomination.
it can't fulfill its obligation
to determine whether it's some other
branch of the vis visible church uh or
whether it's heretical church is
required under the matter or whether
it's a church at all. So I think this
would be a serious mistake.
>> I think my add to that
>> my pragmatism gets in front of my
principles. No.
>> Well, it's okay. But the other thing I
would add is that this kind of creates a
hybrid of 384 or 383 and 384
because it in the prior to the amendment
he is I mean whether whether attempt is
the right word but he is actually
affiliated with some other branch of the
visible church. Um he is a member there.
If you're gonna remove him from your
roles on the basis of his intention, you
have excommunicated him for a period of
time. Um, and and maybe it doesn't work
out. I I intended to do this, but it
didn't work out. That church collapsed
the next Sunday or something along those
lines. Now, you have an individual that
is excommunicated
u while at least
prior to them actually affiliating by uh
or affiliating
they are at least still part of the
visible church. They're they're members
of your church. So I think from what
David said and then the fact that it's a
functional excommunication
while somebody's just looking for
another church. Um and I would also say
that a member's
lack of understanding I'll say it
politely of our polity
doesn't create a crisis for us. Right?
They're they're not understanding what
it means to not be a member in good
standing of an evangelical church
doesn't create a responsibility for me
to simply transfer them to nothing
because they don't want to be a member
of our church anymore. U that's more of
a 384 thing and if that's where they are
then do 384 versus 383A.
Okay.
Overure 13 deals with um commissions by
sessions
and it seemed like several of you
thought this needed to be amended or
just no all together. I'm going to go
with no first. So David, I think you
said no, we don't need this.
>> Right. Um
the uh
I I think that the wording of this is uh
uh not up to what would be needed u in
such an amendment. Um if you allow a
commission to be made up of two members,
uh the quorum proposed would allow one
member to act as a commission.
Um
a session is a deliberative body.
Uh a commission is a smaller
deliberative body. One person is not a
smaller portion of the body and can't be
a deliberative body.
So um
the uh and and I think the BCO affirms
this. Let me say Robert's rules thinks
you can have a committee of one
and uh they don't say anything about
commissions at all but that's partly
what the Robert's reference has to do
with but our BCO says if there's only
one ruling elder he does not constitute
a session
even though he should take spiritual
oversight of the church and report to
the presbyter any matter needing the
action of a church
So if one elder can't be the session,
surely one elder can't be a a
session commission.
>> How are you thinking about this?
>> Well, the overture says the quorum is
the greater of two elders or one half
the membership of the commission. So it
could never be less than two.
Um my concern with this is I mean when I
was on the session of Christ Covenant we
had 44 ruling elders. We had
commissions.
I mean uh
it just uh but I think two is too small.
If you're going to have a judicial
commission, you have to have at least
three. I'd probably make a judicial
commission a quorum of three. I mean um
but
um you know I I don't think it allows a
commission of one. I do think it needs
some amending. Um I would say at least
three with a quorum of two but even then
in a judicial case I can't imagine less
than three. So I think it I think it's
doable but it needs to be tweaked.
>> Steve, what were you you gonna say? Oh,
go ahead David.
>> Yeah. Well, so I I think it would be
helpful to add a statement that
exempts this from judicial commissions.
I think the idea behind this is that
there's lots of things that that
churches can do. Um I mean even
sometimes smaller churches will have a
you know would love to be able to send
two ruling elders to do a membership
interview um perhaps right I mean is it
impossible for the whole session then to
meet? No. But um under certain
circumstances where you might want two
men to be able to not just discuss in a
matter but to but to take action. Um I I
think the fact that both David and I u
maybe it was just the the volume of
reading um read it in such a way that
you could have a commission of just you
know one person. Maybe it needs to be
clearer or we just need to read more
clearly. Uh but I I think that's
something that needs to be cleared up.
So it's crystal clear that you can't
have a commission the quorum for that
commission cannot be less than two under
no circumstances. U and that means if
you have two elders then then they both
have to do all the work and I think
that's fine but but I'm I'm not opposed
to the idea. I think it could be
helpful. Um and certainly the notion
that it doesn't that that the parody at
the session level I don't think is as
important as it is at a presbyary level
or at an assembly level. So I I'm I'm in
favor of the the removal of the concept
of the parody.
U but it tweaks are always a good thing.
So
>> David, what were you going to follow up
on? I I'm content. That's
>> okay.
Okay. Um, what about overture one from
PTOAC about associate assistant pastor
or assistant pastors succeeding the
senior pastor? I think it lowers the
threshold if I remember correctly about
the vote that's needed.
>> David, what do you think? You're
laughing. Uh, I'm laughing because um
the the first amendment that I ever
proposed to the BCA book of church order
was on this section
and the current standard is the standard
that I wrote.
the uh
>> finally finally got around to fixing it.
>> And the reason why I wrote it that way,
very high on both congregational and
presbyter majorities, is because the
earlier language said absolutely
couldn't happen without an intervening
term of service.
First Church Colombia stole our senior
pastor where I was serving as a ruling
out and uh we would have all happily
loved to have our associate take the
senior's position. The whole church
would have done unanimously.
Uh but we had just come into the PCA and
the rule was you can't do it. Um, and so
I wrote it and I knew that there were
people that feared if you allowed this,
you would set up a case where associates
would try and take over for the senior
and undermine them. So I knew it had to
have a very high standard to pass and
that's why I wrote it that way. Well, it
finally did pass, although too late for
us because
First Church Colombia stole our
associate pastor as well.
Uh,
>> no bitterness detected whatsoever.
But um the but since that time um the
thing's been in place, it's been used
and there's never been a case of an
associate being accused of trying to
undermine a senior who even though he
could follow immediately. And so one of
the men in our presbyter came to me and
said, "Look, this is hard for us to do
at this level and we could lower it and
it would still be a very wholesome
thing." And um so we talked about it and
we said, "Let's have a go at it and make
it a little easier since there doesn't
seem it doesn't seem to be a real threat
anymore." That's the point.
>> All right, Steve, you have a have a
different view.
>> Yeah. Well, um I look at it from an
entirely different perspective. Um
80%
is not a high bar.
80% to me is a very low bar for a vote
of a of a congregation to uh receive me
as a pastor. I I don't think I would
take a church if I only got 80% of the
congregation voting in favor of me. So,
I I understand I understand what David
is saying, but when people talk about
80% is a high bar, it's not a high bar.
80% is a is is a low bar to me. Um, I
don't have a problem with Now, that
said, I understand the difference
between my personal feelings about a
high and a low bar and putting it in the
the BCO. This is this is the number you
have to jump over. Um but I just that
language concerns me that we're of high
versus low bar. Um I've been in a church
well that the church I previously served
in uh
the serving assist associate pastor at
the time failed to reach that bar by one
vote at a congregational meeting.
Now, they did eventually call him,
but they called a a pulpit committee.
The pulpit committee did a national
search and they came back and said, "No,
this is the this is the best guy." And I
thought he all along, I thought he was
the best guy. But I I've at least seen
one situation where that guy didn't get
the vote. And it and and again, in that
situation, it wasn't because they didn't
like him. It's because they thought they
were I think they were getting a guy
sort of shoved down their throat versus
the national search piece. So, I'm not
entirely opposed to changing it. Um, but
it's just that that language of low or
high bar just gets to me. That's that's
it. And maybe that's a personal thing
that I just need to get over. Um, but uh
I think the the bigger issue is the
presbyter on a certain level, right?
Because if if if a congregation wants to
call a guy and he's done a really good
job of getting rid of the the previous
pastor, then the congregation is going
to love him and they're all going to
vote for him. And it and it requires in
that sense, I think, the court, the
higher court to make that determination
um potentially before the congregation
votes. But anyway, so that's all I
wanted to say. Well, and sometimes it's
easy to just pick up the phone,
>> talk to the um senior pastor and say,
"How'd this how did this all go down?"
And he can tell you or he could decide
not to tell you, but that's going to
tell you a whole lot more than the
votes. So,
>> okay.
>> So, I think I like I think I like number
one. Okay.
>> Okay. Yeah. Uh let's move along to
overure 55 um from Southwest Florida
about the tenure of assistant pastors. I
think all of you opposed this but I
think it's worth noting because this
question of the the role of an assistant
pastor and what what it plays in our
polity keeps coming up in various ways
over different years. Um why should this
not be voted uh in favor?
I would say because uh uh I would like
the freedom
as a session member to hire an assistant
pastor and keep him assistant pastor
forever.
>> Okay.
>> Um I'm not particularly fond of the
office of associate pastor. I've seen a
lot of SJC cases where an associate and
a senior get sideways and you got to
call a congregational meeting to, you
know, you reach a financial agreement
with the associate. He submits a letter
of resignation, but he's not immediately
going to another call. People think that
smells funny. They want to know what,
you know, what's going on. And I'm a big
fan of assistant pastor. So, um, this
might be my least tied for my least
favorite overure.
>> Okay. All right.
>> David, do you have any thoughts on this?
>> You have any thoughts on this?
Well, um,
the I I I have been an assistant pastor,
but I don't think there's any biblical
warrant for that office at all.
Um, and uh, but we have it. And I I I
think that um
I and I wanted to be an assistant pastor
because I wanted my associate to follow
and I knew if I became an associate
and had to go to session meetings that
he'd never be able to lead the session.
So I needed the assistant pastor to not
be a member of the session so that
transition could work. Right. But
otherwise, I don't think there's any
biblical warrant with it. I just live
with it. But I I'm I'm not opposed to it
because of that. Um
I think that there's a complete
misunderstanding here of what uh the
preliminary principles uh have in view
in nine. Um
the um the assistant pastor doesn't
govern in the sense of preliminary
practice principle six and therefore
there is no need that he have the
consent of the non-governed
that's my point
>> I think you know part of that is the
sort of overreach in the overture that
you know by by preaching ing that that
is an authoritative act that
authoritative an author performing an
authoritative act automatically means
that you have authority. Uh because
number one any guest preacher now under
this idea would need the consent of the
govern before he performs that
authoritative act on a particular
Sunday. Uh the other thing it it made
mention of um you know well these guys
have votes at presbyter these guys have
votes at GA they're they're engaging in
the governance of the church. We'll take
that to another logical extension.
No RUF minister should have a vote at
presbyary because they've never been
consented by any govern nor any uh you
know church planner per se or missionary
on the field or a guy teaching seminary.
there's a whole lot of people. Um, and
also even just the concept that well
there's men at at the general presbyter
that my members didn't vote on that
exercise governance over them. Well,
forget about RUF pastors that the the
church down the street has ruling elders
and teaching elders that go to
Presbyterian. Nobody in my congregation
voted for them. So, that whole thing
seemed very odd to me as well. Um, but
then the other thing is is that there is
this kind of undercurrent and it was
more prevalent last year. I think it
might have been changed a little bit
this year in the overture. This idea
that assistant pastors are are just
wrong and bad and and and they shouldn't
be doing this because it it contradicts
a preliminary principle. And my thought
is, well, if it contradicts a
preliminary principle, you shouldn't
have them for five years or five
minutes. It either does or it doesn't.
And it's not, well, it's okay. We can
stomach or hold our nose for five years
even though this contradicts a
preliminary principle and then we have
to make a change to it. Um, and I
suppose I mean the other thing is I
would say is that no no no no man is
ever actually forced to take a call as
an assistant pastor if he's principally
opposed to it. No session is required to
call a man if they disagree with it. um
this this seems to me to be
we don't like it and we want to force
everybody else to do the same thing even
though that forcing really either it is
a biblical principle and nobody should
do it or it's a matter of Christian
prudence and each individual court
should make a determination as to
whether or not they do it.
I'd like to speak up for the ruling
elder union since I'm the only ruling
elder on this call. Um there seems to be
almost an undercurrent idea that
every teaching elder is qualified to be
a session member. So if a 24 year old
guy finishes his MD and we hire him to
be to do a staff job,
uh he must be on the session. Never been
married. doesn't have kids. I can't
evaluate what kind of a husband he is,
what kind of a father he is. Why would I
put him on the session?
I wouldn't put him on the session. I
can't evaluate those critically
important things. I was ordained as an
elder at age 30. And I tell people that
was 10 years too early for me.
I wouldn't put a guy on the session just
cuz he has an MD. No way.
>> All right, guys. I want to move us along
to to wrap us up here with just uh two
more and then if there's others you want
to tap. Let's talk about overture 49
from Northwest Georgia which is to
increase ruling elder representation at
presbyary and general assembly. All
three of you I think said no and one of
you even said this is really bad. So let
I'll just leave that out to you guys to
tackle. Who wants to speak to this?
>> I don't think we should waste time on
it. It's It's a very bad idea.
>> Okay.
>> And it'll never pass. So,
>> David, do you want to say anything about
it? We don't have to say anything more
if that's all that needs to be said.
>> I I just think it's uh it doesn't make
any sense.
We have two entitlements
now for a church of a particular size
and we're not getting enough ruling
elders. So, we're going to add another
entitlement.
How is that going to get more ruling
elders? I I don't
You're going to get more ruling elders
when you start having general assembly
and airline hubs.
>> All right, that's another one of How's
soap boxes there, right? All right,
>> tech project.
>> All right, last one then. Um I think
this is kind of a repeat of last year.
Overture 68 from Kataba on committee and
agency appointees not getting a vote on
the administrative committee. Um,
didn't we deal with this last year? Uh,
or is it is there a slight difference?
It may be slightly different, but I
don't think it's substantially
different.
Last year a similar overture
um was uh referred to all the permanent
committees and the agency boards as it
is this year.
Uh last year eight of the 10 committee
of commissioners
supported the permanent committee and
the agency boards by answering James
River nine in the negative.
RUF committee commissioners didn't vote
on it and uh surprisingly MTW committee
commissioners voted to affirm it by vote
of 29 to 21.
Uh nobody wants this
except the 29 guys on
>> guys on
>> one committee of commissioners. Well,
and I mean for me, I think this goes
back to something I said, you know, in
the previous that um this is this is a
feature of our permanent committees and
agencies. Um and so
while it does
uh to a certain degree you might say it
dilutes the voting power of the actual
members who were elected by the assembly
to the administrative committee and I
and I get that argument that that that's
true but the question then becomes
is that
of necessity had
um when you have a committee like AC
that deals with matters that extend
beyond mean well it just it extends into
the entirety of the of the denomination.
I mean it would be one thing if we said
every committee gets a voting member on
every other committee
like okay I could understand why that
would be a bad thing. M&A or MTW now all
of a sudden gets 11 or whatever extra
members that go in from these other
committees or nine I suppose that go in.
But admin of its nature deals with
issues that that are of the entire
assembly, the assembly but also the
denomination. And to have those men on
there as as voting members uh is is
fine. I don't I don't think there's any
necessarily any problem with that. And I
think this kind of just goes back to um
you know people reacting to
what something that sounds like it is
intended to stack a deck or something
along those lines and that's uh I I just
don't I don't see that as the necessary
result of this process. It's a potential
result, sure, but it's not a necessary
consequence of having agency appointees
uh be voting members of the AC. Um and
so unless there's a a a clearer argument
against it, um I don't think it's all
that important. and and plus it failed
last year unless there's some new major
thing that I don't know about that's
gonna bring this as a wave and and and
all of a sudden it's going to get
passed. Um and I memory serves this is
this is a BCO amendment.
Um even so I mean it's not just that it
has to pass one assembly now it has to
pass two assemblies and uh twothirds of
presbyaries. So um
I just don't see it as as it's not going
to pass. So there's not really even any
real reason to discuss it and to try to
push it forward. I think the other thing
to remember is that none of the um
permanent committee or agency board
appointees were unelected by the
assembly. They were all elected by the
assembly with the full knowledge that
maybe they become an appointee to the
AC. I mean it's maybe not that that
clear to everybody but they weren't just
appointed by the seminary board. They
were appointed by the GA elected
seminary board. So,
>> yep.
All right. Is are there any other
administrative or polity overtures that
you all think we need to discuss?
>> Could I offer one last word on this
subject?
>> Please. Please, David. it. If we think
about it abstractly,
we might have thought
that it was absolutely proper for each
committee and agency
to prepare their own budget and present
it to the assembly.
That would have been the natural thing
to think of.
But for certain credential reasons, we
decided better to have all those budgets
be handled by one committee.
But then we thought, well, of course
then if if we're not going to have the
committees present their own budgets,
certainly there ought to be somebody
from the committee on admin to represent
and advocate the cause of that
committee. And it seems to me like it
was a perfect credential
uh um
scheme to fulfill two concerns. One that
there be a unified sense and use of the
monies of the assembly but without
excluding altogether from inbut to that
body from the committees and agencies.
Um, I don't see this as in any sense a
defect. I think it's a a mark of wisdom.
I'd like to put in a plug for PTOAC 81
proposing to change the RAO to require
wine and juice at the General Assembly
Lord's Supper. I chaired the host
committee in Charlotte in 2003 and I was
explicitly and energetically told we
could not use wine and I thought the
person with authority was being
facitious but they weren't. Um so we
deferred to that but um
it it kind of shocked me and surprised
me but so I like PTOIC 81.
>> Interesting. Uh, okay. So, backing up to
RAO, I mean, I I thought that one was
curious. Uh, Steve, I'd love to hear
your thoughts on that. Do you do you
think that uh we should require wine to
be served at General Assembly Communion?
>> Only if Howie buys it. Um,
>> no. I
>> then I'd like to buy the cups, too,
because they'll be a little bit bigger.
>> Yeah. The only the only question I might
have is whether
facilities might have any issue with
that, but even then it's for religious
purpose. I I would think even in that
case it wouldn't matter. But
>> so in that sense maybe require is too
strong a word because what if you end up
in an area where
>> they just say flat out you cannot bring
alcoholic beverages on site altogether.
But, you know, the the concept of saying
we're never going to serve what actually
ought to be served in the Lord's supper
seems to me uh to be a bad idea. And
certainly providing the option u I mean
not the option but I mean in the sense
of both are present uh makes sense to
me. And the first assembly we have this
I will buy the Molly Duker blue-eyed boy
Shiraz from South Australia.
>> All right. Well, we've got that.
>> Mark my words.
>> Mark my words. I'm glad it's recorded.
>> All right, gentlemen. Is there anything
else before I I close this up here?
>> Okay. Well,
>> thank you for doing Thank you for doing
this.
>> I'm very grateful to you all. I do hope
that this can be a model of how we can
talk about things in the PCA. I know all
of us come from different places and uh
we want to be able to talk about these
things respectfully, charitably, uh
assuming the best and hopefully in a way
that sharpens us so that we can discern
the spirit's work in our in our
denomination and make wise decisions
together. So, I appreciate the way you
guys are contributing to hopefully
promoting that. Uh and we'll we'll all
be in prayer about Louisville and the
decisions we have before us there. I
know you guys will be working um
together still to put out some comments
on your overure uh advice and also just
even docket order. So uh viewers, you
want to keep an eye out for those um so
that can help you think about uh the
overures yourselves. All right. Well,
thank you again, gentlemen, and thank
you all for listening.
>> Amen. Thank you.